Wow, this is authentic Cantonese food.
>> I practiced so much Cantonese for this
episode.
Oh, no.
All right, we're going to make char siu
char siu pork roast. We're going to be
making this Cantonese, but not really
Cantonese
export specific red pink Cantonese junk
food street food roast pork. Put simply,
it is a shoulder of pig, a Boston butt,
or a collar marinated with
nonsense
and roasted gently until it's sticky and
brown and priapic and stiff. Uh it is
usually served sliced, chopped up on
rice, or on noodles in a cha chan teng.
Which is the Cantonese version of a
diner. Nowadays, it also shows up very
prevalently in the West, the glorious
West. Because it's one of the few dishes
that later in [music] life was modified
extensively and designed for the whites.
Sweet, sticky, jizzy, bright, it's
Chinese food. So, a lot of the times
when an Englishman says, "Would you like
a Chinese?"
he means a char siu. But today we're
going to try to make the traditional
version and talk about some history. My
goal today is to surprise and edumacate
my Cantonese friend. Yeah, you're going
to realize that Lao Chen, we say he's
[music] Cantonese, but he's actually Diu
Siu Lam. Yes, which is not Cantonese. It
is his dialect, and they are first and
foremost Diu Siu Lam and not Guangdong
ren. I'm learning. I don't speak
Cantonese, I'm learning as I go. So,
feel free to correct me cuz I know
there's a lot of you, you sneaky little
[__]
from Hong Kong and all over the world.
Uh first, you're going to need to talk
about your meat. I have here the
shoulder in question. This is In
America, you would call it the butt, the
Boston butt, even though it's not
anywhere near the butt. If you're
Australian, then you might call it the
collar or the cop
pa. Anyways, it's just a shoulder meat.
It's the part that's fatty and chunky
without the bone. If you can, get a hold
of this, which is the entire section,
the cross-section. So, this sits on Lao
Chen, come over here.
Just just just come here.
We have this So, this sits here. This is
where it's from.
It's here. It's this this is this
section, yeah? So, this part of him. So,
um you want this big chunk so you can
then slice it into big slabs. How thin
or how thick is entirely up to you. This
will shrink a lot in the cooking, and I
like a thick slab of char siu, so I will
slice it thicker. You can go thinner if
you want, and by thick I mean this, like
a double thick stick. All right? And
this after sliced can go back in
the container. If you can, you can also
buy in your Chinese grocer's pork butt
that's been sliced already quite thin.
This is also acceptable if you don't
want to go through that. As you can
tell, the Cantonese guy, the si fu,
butterflied this because he couldn't get
a nice big slice. It used to look like
this,
and he just cut it once like that and
opened it up, which is also fine. So, I
don't have to show you how to do it. All
right? I bought three different kinds of
meat so you can see the difference in
age, in breed, and in freshness. So,
this was probably slaughtered today. It
hasn't had much time to to soak up
oxygen, which is why it's kind of like
this grayish hazy. This has been packed
with gases to make it look pink and
rosy, which is why most people think
it's fresh. This is like pretty much a
couple days out, yeah? So, I prefer
this. Yeah, it still has the warmth of
the pig on it. All right, we're going to
do the marinade now. Why are we making
this? Well, first of all, it's because a
lot of people asked us to. It's It seems
to be a very popular dish in um the
West. I almost never order this dish. I
don't like sticky sweet meat. It's not
my idea of a good way to spend money,
but it is for a lot of people. And if
you wanted to introduce someone to
Chinese food that's still authentic, but
also acceptable internationally, this is
where [music] I would start. So, if you
had like the kid who grew up on only
white food, who looks at a bowl of ramen
and goes, "Is that cooked?" this is
where [music] you would start. All
right, so this is my ginger. Feel free
to peel it or not, it doesn't really
matter. If you want to peel it, just
scrape it down with the back of your
knife. After it's been peeled, feel free
to slice it down, and you're good to go.
The ginger and the garlic are up to you
ratio-wise. Uh there's no real right or
wrong way to do this, but for the sake
of a recipe, let's make one as we go,
shall we? This is ginger, call it 25,
and 40 g of garlic, 200 of soy sauce,
100 of cooking wine, and 200 g of
maltose. If you don't have what the [__]
ever, use honey. Nam Yu, red fermented
bean curd product. It's like salted tofu
chunks soaked in brine, left to ferment.
It is essentially our version of
Roquefort or Stilton or Gorgonzola. It's
blue cheese. It's one of the delicious
delicious things we use to flavor a lot
of dishes from the north all the way
down to the south. In this application,
almost never use the cubes, I just use
the juice. Okay, that's 50. If you can
get a hold of it, hung chui, which is a
fermented rice that goes kind of this
beautiful burgundyish red, which is
where the color is from in traditional
char siu. It doesn't really lend a
flavor, it doesn't really matter much
for the dish. If you really care about
the color, feel free to use red coloring
and a little bit of purple, especially
if you want that UK version. We use this
traditionally because of the naturally
occurring color compounds. It's not very
pH or temperature sensitive. By that, I
mean like, you know, cabbage and red
onions? You know how they go red and
pink and purple and blue? Uh sometimes
when you heat it up, when you cool it
down, when you add acid, when you add
baking soda. Those are called
temperature and pH sensitive. These
don't really change much color over
temperature. So, 70 to 80, doesn't
matter.
And this is what I wanted to talk to you
about later, but we'll get to that in a
sec. All right? Now, the last OH, [__]
[__] [__] [laughter] [__] [__] OKAY.
THE last ingredient I didn't put in,
hoisin sauce or haixianjiang. 150. If
you want a Westernized, but still
authentic Wan Qing Ming Guo immigrant
Cantonese version of char siu, you would
use hoisin sauce. If you want a Chinese
version, you would probably use
tianmianjiang. I'll tell you why in a
bit.
There we go. And here is our marinade.
Super red, right? Yeah, it's beautiful.
Now, the last thing that we need to do
is add five spice. Why does my
RESTAURANT NOT HAVE FIVE SPICE IN IT?
All right, time to make some [__]
five spice. This is my recipe for five
spice, not the recipe for five spice,
okay? So, don't get your
titties all twisted up. 4 g of cinnamon,
6 g of Sichuan peppercorn, a couple
cloves, usually 1 g, I don't even bother
measuring it. 5 g of star anise. Did I
already add fennel seeds?
Whatever, [__] it. Four or five spices,
doesn't matter. Here we go, and wooshy
woosh.
All right, cool. So, this has been
blending for a couple minutes now. So,
pork goes in, and in goes my marinade.
All right, so this delicious dark red
nonsense is our pork.
Perfecto. Okay, cool.
Um so, here is our pork. Can live in
this marinade up to 2 days. The longer
you marinate it, the more obvious the
outside redness becomes. This
will then live inside my fridge on top
of a baking tray. There we go. Done.
Easy. And that lives in the fridge.
That will marinate for a while, and then
tomorrow we will come back and bake it.
In that time, would you guys like to
learn a bit about history? So, first of
all, char siu, these two words put
together, when you listen to this
overseas in the West and you hear,
"Let's go get some char siu." Those two
words, Cantonese, it's a Latin writing
of two Cantonese pronunciations of the
words cha shao, literally translates
into forked roast. The forked roast, the
roasting of meats
goes all the way back to I want to say
the Song Dynasty, roughly 800, 900 years
ago. And the idea of the roasting of
meats on a spit with a fork, this was a
cookery method used to process a lot of
meats, and it was used to show wealth,
the same way that in medieval Europe,
European lords and ladies and dukes and
viscounts [music] and [__] would have
invited their friends and their douchey
fatty lord friends over to the manor or
the castle to enjoy a roast beast. The
roasting of meats, the correct roasting
of meats was a symbol of wealth. If you
really think about it, Han culture is
the Song Dynasty. The long flowy silk
robes. They were all busy writing poems,
playing lutes, and boys. And then the
Mongolians showed up, and that [__] had
to end immediately. Like the Song
Dynasty was the most culturally
influential and important episode, in my
opinion, of what can be considered Han
[snorts]
Chinese culture. So, with this being
said, char siu is actually kind of
correct because Cantonese and
Shanghainese originate from medieval Han
Chinese, which is why How do you say
yi er san si wu liu qi ba jiu shi in
Cantonese?
How do you say it in Shanghainese?
Sounds familiar, right? Not the same as
yi er san si wu liu qi ba jiu shi. You
can hear the the language roots in
medieval Chinese. So, anyways, that was
a tangent. So, the idea is that this
roasting of meats went on for a long
time, but in the south, especially in
the Guangdong Guangxi areas, the
roasting of meats became more systematic
in the besume system of making things.
So, your roast goose, your roast duck,
your char siu, your roast chicken, these
things were part of the Cantonese way of
roasting things. You could buy ready
roasted meats, saucy and delicious. That
was when this whole story started, and
that went on further and further until
the late Qing Dynasty. It was during
this time that a lot of
Cantonese people started leaving Canton.
Some went to build the railroads, some
went for business, some went to
Southeast Asia, some went across the
Pacific and they brought their flavors
with them. But during this time there
was a very very important person and any
single one of you who have ever made
Chinese food overseas already knows his
name. You pronounce it Lee Kum Kee. The
company Lee Kum Kee. Lee Kum Kee.
Cool. Thank you. But that's not his
name, that's just the name of his
company. In the same reason that this
company is CKK. Chun Chee Kee.
Kee as in legacy or memory or story.
That is a very Cantonese way to name
your company. So Lee Kum Kee. Southern
company of seasonings and sauces. This
man was from late Qing Dynasty Canton in
Zhuhai. That's where his business
started. It was a Zhuhai company. His
actual name was Lee Kum Sheung. Cool.
The character in this name literally has
a monk on the top and clothing on the
bottom. It was a unisex undergarment
dress. Women and men both wore it. It
was just this open-ended thing to keep
your crotch nice and room temperature
while you went around like a lord
directing your business. So Lee Kum
Sheung was the owner of this company. He
established his company Lee Kum Kee in
1888. Which is why on all the bottles
you see 1888 1888 1888. So after the
last episode of the Qing Dynasty, the
writing got very bad. The show fell
apart and he
off to
Macau.
Macau first. Which is why Lee Kum Kee is
in Macanese Macau company. And then from
Macau he expanded his business into Hong
Kong but simultaneously internationally.
So these Chinese immigrants, the
Cantonese people who grew up on this
sauce would take these sauces from Lee
Kum Kee and go all the way to Vancouver,
San Francisco, California, America, the
new world. On the backs of Cantonese
immigrants were the
base foundation sauces that built a lot
of western Cantonese cuisine. Which is
why in mainland China to this day
because hoisin is a combination of tin
min jeung tong tsui and tiao wei.
There's no seafood in it. It wasn't
meant for seafood.
That's why it's called hoisin sauce.
Hoisin sauce is a Lee Kum Kee creation
created to be a dip because western
people want to dip. When western people
see this [__]
they think of a dip. When we see this we
think of ingredients to cook with. So a
good Chinese chef on the mainland would
make his own sauce. Which is why in the
north in Beijing in Peking duck you
serve it with tin min jeung. But in the
west you serve duck with hoisin sauce.
Yeah. Hoisin sauce is a creation of
sugar, vinegar,
They standardized They made it
manufacturable so that at every
restaurant Chinese restaurants is all
those whites they want something sweet
and sour. [__] [__] [__] [__] [__] and
they go
Wow, this is authentic Cantonese food.
But in in in China you would never you
would never make that sauce. There's no
right or wrong, it's just how the two
stories developed. This is why in the
west hoisin sauce is used in this
recipe. In mainland China you would use
tin min jeung with extra sugar and
vinegar.
I practiced so much Cantonese for this
episode.
So
this dish then developed in the west
as alongside China at the exact same
time that in China char siu became a cha
chan teng thing. It became a tiao tou
mei shi thing. A shuk shi dong thing. A
deli thing. A diner thing. So too did it
in the west become a restaurant staple
and a family staple. So a Cantonese
mother of three kids trying to put them
through college at UCLA or UC Santa
Barbara or this that and the other or
New York University or whatever. My son
going to be doctor, engineer, whatever.
But I want him to eat like a Cantonese
person. And she goes to the store she
goes ah deal
She brings it back. Well this is all we
have. And she owns a restaurant to serve
the public. And when the westerners the
New Yorkers goes like what where's the
[__] sauce? Hoisin sauce. Yeah.
That's where the story came from.
So Lee Kum Kee made Chinese flavors of
Canton international. But they're not
representative of mainland flavors.
Think about it. The brand here is not
Lee Kum Kee. We do not really buy Lee
Kum Kee. We buy other brands. We buy Mok
Kee and more others, right? Lee Kum Kee
very rarely cuz it's expensive. Wait.
They're more successful overseas than
they are here in the mainland. I'm
sorry. We were we were here to cook and
I ended up talking. Anyways, I will see
you guys tomorrow for the reveal when we
bake it and we serve it. Sound good?
Cool. All right. Welcome back guys. It's
been 24 hours. Had some meetings. Had
of a lunch service and just realized
that I still have to finish this video.
So what had happened was I took the meat
out of the marinade separated to big and
small chunks on two shallow half pans.
[music] Reserved the marinade and threw
that into an oven at 150° C roughly 300
and a tiny bit degrees Fahrenheit
[music]
at 100% humidity and I pulled 2 hours.
If you have humidity use it if you're a
show-off like me. If you don't then just
put it into a slightly deeper vessel and
[music] wrap it in tin foil or baking
paper for the bake. Now after an hour
the meat's going to look something like
this. My colleagues were nice enough to
put it [music] all onto one tray for me.
As you can see these are big.
These are chunky. This is the big chunks
and the small chunks. They started life
the story in two separate pans but now
they are in the same pan. I like big and
steak-y but more traditional char siu
hay gum char siu
would be this. Thin, slightly chewy, a
little bit sticky on the edges. And my
marinade
has been strained through a mesh
strainer to get rid of the bigger chunky
bits and then cooked until boiling and
then taken off the heat. The reason we
do that is because this is not a
marinade that needs to be reduced. It's
already very very heavily flavored and
if you cook it the starches inside the
red rice will actually thicken the paste
almost like a gochujang from Korea. If
you didn't have the red rice and used
red food coloring instead feel free at
this point to add a cornstarch slurry to
thicken it up. Yeah? And then we're
going to use this brush liberally onto
our mostly cooked hay gum char siu. You
want to be as generous as you possibly
can be because this is not a lightly
flavored roast meat with a little bit of
salt and pepper on the outside. This is
meant to be a heavily flavored pork
candy roast that can be eaten in small
flavorful chunks atop white rice. Which
is how it would be served in cha chan
teng. In a western sense this pork would
be poorly done. Because it would be too
overcooked for a roast and too
undercooked for a barbecue which would
be falling apart at the seams. But
remember in Asian food there's more
actual meat texture in a roast. There's
more bounciness. We don't believe that
chewing is a mortal sin so we don't mind
a little bit of chew in the texture. So
in again it goes to tighten up the glaze
at 150 again and we should be able to
get away with a 5-minute cook. In this 5
minutes it's probably smart to prepare
some fried eggs for the top of your
rice. rice itself. Here are my fried
eggs. Crispy snappy
on the outside. This is the correct
doneness of egg for a Cantonese cha chan
teng bowl of rice. You want the egg
whites to be undercooked.
All right. So if you want to blanch your
lettuce in my opinion the easiest way is
to put it into a sealable container with
one of the edges cracked just like that
to vent a little bit. And then you just
let it ride for 45 seconds. The steam
will be generated from the liquid inside
the vegetable itself so you don't have
to bring a pot of water to the boil like
some [__] That was so BBC again I'm
talking to one camera and for no reason
at all
I've turned to this one. Oh I love that
move. So after another 5 minutes in the
oven we're ready to come back.
[__] Okay. That's tightened up the
We're ready guys.
>> [clears throat]
>> This is 45 seconds inside the microwave.
As you can see perfectly blanched. While
it's still hot I'm going to throw in a
little bit of confit garlic that we have
for service. Just mashed up garlic
cooked gently in oil until everything's
soft.
Ah that smells right. That smells
absolutely correct now. And a little bit
of soy sauce on top
just to season your vegetable. That goes
over here off to one side. I'm going to
grab something nice and roasty and
beautiful and red and deeply colored.
Cut as thick or as thin as you want.
This would be considered a very very
generous portion.
Usually it's considered polite to serve
a little bit of lean char siu and some
fat char siu all in one bowl.
Eat your vegetable down.
If you had an hour or two
of hard work and an evening of sleep
handy for a weekend food project that
keeps well, stores forever, heats up
beautifully and gives maximum
satisfaction for minimum effort it would
really be hard to beat this. You could
put salt and pepper and butter on a
chicken and wait for an hour and a half
and start two more pots to reduce a
stock and make a gravy and then put it
on mashed potatoes. But if we're
perfectly honest veg plus starch plus
meat for less effort and more flavor
I prefer this. It's proof positive you
don't have to put MSG in everything. But
that being said we put like a whole cup
of soy sauce inside, so
close it up.
Anyways, I hopefully this was useful to
you. Let's recap.
All ingredients in a blender, put it
over your pork, marinate anywhere
between 12 to 48 hours depending on how
flavorful you like it. Bake at 150.
Full moisture if you have a moisture
setting in your oven. If not, cover it
with foil for the first hour.
Uncover it for the next half an hour
while you baste and bake.
If you don't want to baste, then bake it
with its own sauce and then let it
run dry without a covering.
Uh and that might help. You'll get most
of the way there. If you want to baste,
it doesn't make a huge difference,
[music] but it does add to the theater
of it.
Don't need to rest it. Don't let it cool
down. Whip it out and then serve it on
top of rice with fried egg and some
blanched lettuce. Done. You have meals
for [music] a week.
Meal prep? Perfect.
Easy weeknight dinner? Perfect. You want
it to have a sense of occasion?
Perfect.
>> [music]
>> You want to make Cantonese friends?
Perfect. I already told you the tricks,
guys. Can peanut oil and now this.
Chasiu and huasheng you, right? You just
fry something in peanut oil, fry two
eggs in peanut oil and then make some
chasiu and you'll
I guarantee. Anyways, comment, like,
subscribe. Talk often, talk soon. Take
care, guys. We'll see you for the next
one. Let me know what else you want to
learn.
>> [clears throat]
>> Good team. Good team. Good team. Good
team.